recording all librivox recordings are in the public domain for more information
or to volunteer please visit librivox.org this recording by jay Hall
The Wonderful Wizard of Oz by L. Frank Baum Chapter one The Cyclone Dorothy
lived in the midst of the great Kansas prairies, with Uncle Henry, who was a
farmer, and Aunt Em, who was the farmer’s wife. Their house was small, for the
lumber to build it had to be carried by wagon many miles. There were four walls
floor and a roof, which made one room; and this room contained a rusty looking cook
stove a cupboard for the dishes, a table, three or four chairs, and the beds. Uncle Henry
in Aunt Em had a big bed in one corner, and Dorothy a little bed in another
corner. There was no garret at all, and no cellar— —except a small hole dug in the
ground, called a cyclone cellar, where the family could go in case one of those
great world winds arose, mighty enough to crush any building in its path. It was
reached by a trapdoor in the middle of the floor, from which a ladder led down
into the small, dark hole. When Dorothy stood in the doorway and looked around,
she could see nothing but the great gray prairie on every side. Not a tree nor
house broke the broad sweep of flat country that reached to the edge of the
sky in all directions. The sun had baked the ploughed land into a gray mass, with
little cracks running through it. Even the grass was not green, for the sun had
burned the tops of the long blades until they were the same gray color to be seen
everywhere. Once the house had been painted, but the sun blistered the paint
and the rains washed it away, and now the house was as dull and gray as everything
else. When Aunt Em came there to live she was a young, pretty wife. The sun and wind
had changed her, too. They had taken the sparkle from her eyes and left them a
sober gray; they had also taken the red from her cheeks and lips, and they were a
grey also. She was thin and gaunt, and never smiled now. When Dorothy, who was an
orphan, first came to her nm had been so startled by the child’s laughter that
she would scream and press her hands upon her heart whenever Dorothy’s merry
voice reached her ears; and she still looked at the little girl with wonder
that she could find anything to laugh at.
Uncle Henry never laughed. He worked hard from morning till night and did not know
what joy was. He was gray also, from his long beard to his rough boots, and he
looked stern and solemn, and rarely spoke.
It was Toto that made Dorothy laugh, and saved her from growing his gray as her
other surroundings photo was not gray; he was a little black
with long silky hair and small black eyes that twinkled merrily on either
side of his funny we nose. Toto played all day long, and Dorothy played with him,
and loved him dearly. Today, however, they were not playing.
Uncle Henry sat upon the doorstep and looked anxiously at the sky, which was
even greater than usual. Dorothy stood in the door with Toto in her arms, and
looked at the sky too and M was washing the dishes. From the far north they heard
a low wail of the wind, and Uncle Henry and Dorothy could see with the long
grass bowed in waves before the coming storm.
There now came a sharp whistling in the air from the south, and as they turned
their eyes that way they saw ripples in the grass coming from that direction
also. Suddenly Uncle Henry stood up.
“There’s a cyclone coming in he called to his wife. “I’ll go look after the stock.”
Then he ran toward the sheds where the cows and horses were kept. Aunt Em
dropped her work and came to the door.
One glance told her of the danger close at hand. “Quick, Dorothy!” she screamed. “Run
for the cellar!” Toto jumped out of Dorothy’s arms and hid under the bed, and
the girl started to get him and M badly frightened, threw open the trapdoor in
the floor and climbed down the ladder into the small, dark hole. Dorothy caught
Toto at last and started to follow her aunt. When she was halfway across the
room there came a great shriek from the wind, and the house shook so hard that
she lost her footing and sat down suddenly upon the floor. Then a strange
thing happened. The house whirled around two or three times and rose slowly
through the air. Dorothy felt as if she were going up in a balloon north and
south winds met where the house stood, and made it the exact center of the
cyclone. In the middle of a cyclone the air is generally still, but the great
pressure of the wind on every side of the house raised it up higher and higher,
until it was at the very top of the cyclone; and there it remained and was
carried miles and miles away as easily as you could carry a feather. It was very
dark, and the wind howled horribly around her, but Dorothy found she was riding
quite easily. After the first few whirls around, and another one time when the
house tipped badly, she felt as if she were being rocked
gently, like a baby in a cradle. Toto did not like it. He ran about the room, now
here, now they're barking loudly; but Dorothy's at quite still on the floor
and waited to see what would happen. Once Toto got too near the open trapdoor and
fell in; and at first the little girl thought she had lost him. But soon she
saw one of his ears sticking up through the hole, for the strong pressure of the
air was keeping him up so that he could not fall. She crept to the hole, caught
total by the year and dragged him into the room again, afterward closing the
trap door so that no more accidents could happen. Hour after hour passed away,
and slowly Dorothy got over her fright; but she felt quite lonely, and the wind
shrieks so loudly all about her that she nearly became death At first she wonder
if she would be dashed to pieces when the house fell again; but as the hours
passed and nothing terrible happened, she stopped worrying and resolved to
wait calmly and see what the future would bring. At last she crawled over the
swaying floor to her bed, and lay down upon it; and Toto followed and laid down
beside her. In spite of the swaying of the house and the wailing of the wind,
Dorothy soon closed her eyes and fell fast asleep this is a librivox recording